<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Peter Kuma Software and Science</title>
<description></description>
<link>/</link>







<item>
<title>Poster | Climate model code genealogy and its relation to sensitivity and feedbacks</title>
<author>Kuma et al.</author>
<description>Contemporary general circulation models and Earth system models are developed by a large group of modelling centres internationally. They use a broad range of implementations of climate dynamics and physical parametrisations, allowing for structural (code) uncertainty to be partially quantified with multi-model ensembles (MMEs). However, many models in the MMEs of the Climate Model Intercomparison Project (CMIP) have a common development history due to the widespread practice of sharing of code and parametrisations within and between modelling centres. This makes results from different models statistically dependent, potentially introducing biases in MME statistics. This situation became more pronounced in CMIP6 compared to CMIP5 due to the proliferation of model runs contributed by the same model, and due to the fact that several models predict much higher effective climate sensitivity (ECS) than multiple evidence assessments such as the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change Sixth Assessment Report, and this means that some MME statistics differ from multiple evidence estimates. Previous research investigating effects of model inter-dependence has focused on model output and code dependence, but model code genealogy of CMIP models has not been fully analysed. We present a full reconstruction of CMIP3, CMIP5 and CMIP6 model code genealogy based on available literature and online resources, with a focus on inheritance in the atmospheric component and atmospheric physical parametrisations. We developed a `fair' model code weighting method based on the model code genealogy for the purpose of analysing the impact of such weighting on MME means. We assess the implications of such weighting on ECS, climate feedbacks, forcing and global mean near-surface air temperature, as well as simpler weighting methods based on model family, institute and country in CMIP5 and CMIP6. In some cases the impact is found to be substantial and can partially reconcile the differences in MME means between CMIP5 and CMIP6. We show that some model families have a propensity to be relatively warm or cold in the main CMIP5 and CMIP6 experiments. Our method is complementary to the existing methods based on model output clustering. The presented results can help in understanding of structural dependencies between CMIP models, and the proposed code and family weighting methods can be used in MME assessments to ameliorate model structure sampling biases.</description>
<link>/science/posters/kuma_et_al_2022/</link>
<guid>/science/posters/kuma_et_al_2022/</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
<enclosure url="/science/posters/kuma_et_al_2022/Kuma%20et%20al.%20(2022),%20Climate%20model%20code%20genealogy%20and%20its%20relation%20to%20sensitivity%20and%20feedbacks.pdf" length="2364375" type="application/pdf" />
</item>







<item>
<title>Article | Machine learning of cloud types in satellite observations and climate models</title>
<author>Kuma et al.</author>
<description>Uncertainty in cloud feedbacks in climate models is a major limitation in projections of future climate. Therefore, evaluation and improvement of cloud simulation is essential to ensure the accuracy of climate models. We analyse cloud biases and cloud change with respect to global mean near-surface temperature (GMST) in climate models relative to satellite observations, and relate them to equilibrium climate sensitivity, transient climate response and cloud feedback. For this purpose, we develop a supervised deep convolutional artificial neural network for determination of cloud types from low-resolution (2.5°×2.5°) daily mean top of atmosphere shortwave and longwave radiation fields, corresponding to the World Meteorological Organization (WMO) cloud genera recorded by human observers in the Global Telecommunication System (GTS). We train this network on a top of atmosphere radiation retrieved by the Clouds and the Earth’s Radiant Energy System (CERES) and GTS, and apply it on the Climate Model Intercomparison Project phase 5 and 6 (CMIP5 and CMIP6) model output and the ECMWF Reanalysis version 5 (ERA5) and the Modern-Era Retrospective Analysis for Research and Applications version 2 (MERRA-2) reanalyses. We compare the cloud types between models and satellite observations. We link biases to climate sensitivity and identify a negative linear relationship between the root mean square error of cloud type occurrence derived from the neural network and model equilibrium climate sensitivity (ECS), transient climate response (TCR) and cloud feedback. This statistical relationship in the model ensemble favours models with higher ECS, TCR and cloud feedback. However, this relationship could be due to the relatively small size of the ensemble used or decoupling between present-day biases and future projected cloud change. Using the abrupt-4xCO2 CMIP5 and CMIP6 experiment, we show that models simulating decreasing stratiform and increasing cumuliform clouds tend to have higher ECS than models simulating increasing stratiform and decreasing cumuliform clouds, and this could also be partially responsible for the difference in ECS observed.</description>
<link>/science/papers/kuma_et_al_2022/</link>
<guid>/science/papers/kuma_et_al_2022/</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 07 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<enclosure url="/science/papers/kuma_et_al_2022/Kuma%20et%20al.%20(2022),%20Machine%20learning%20of%20cloud%20types%20in%20satellite%20observations%20and%20climate%20models%20(submitted%20revision%2022%20July%202022).pdf" length="10464157" type="application/pdf" />
</item>







<item>
<title>Article | Detection of supercooled liquid water containing clouds with ceilometers: development and evaluation of deterministic and data-driven retrievals</title>
<author>Guyot et al.</author>
<description>Cloud and aerosol lidars measuring backscatter and depolarization ratio are the most suitable lidars to detect cloud phase (liquid, ice, or mixed phase). However, such instruments are not widely deployed as part of operational networks. In this study, we propose a new algorithm to detect supercooled liquid water containing clouds (SLCC) based on ceilometers measuring only co-polarization backscatter. We utilize observations collected at Davis, Antarctica, where low-level, mixed-phase clouds, including supercooled liquid water (SLW) droplets and ice crystals, remain poorly understood due to the paucity of ground-based observations. A 3-month set of observations were collected during the austral summer of November 2018 to February 2019, with a variety of instruments including a depolarization lidar and a W-band cloud radar which were used to build a two-dimensional cloud phase mask distinguishing SLW and mixed-phase clouds. This cloud phase mask is used as the reference to develop a new algorithm based on the observations of a single polarization ceilometer operating in the vicinity for the same period. Deterministic and data-driven retrieval approaches were evaluated: an extreme gradient boosting (XGBoost) framework ingesting backscatter average characteristics was the most effective method at reproducing the classification obtained with the combined radar–lidar approach with an accuracy as high as 0.91. This study provides a new SLCC retrieval approach based on ceilometer data and highlights the considerable benefits of these instruments to provide intelligence on cloud phase in polar regions that usually suffer from a paucity of observations. Finally, the two algorithms were applied to a full year of ceilometer observations to retrieve cloud phase and frequency of occurrences of SLCC: SLCC was present 29 ± 6 % of the time for T19 and 24 ± 5 % of the time for G22-Davis over that annual cycle.</description>
<link>/science/papers/guyot_et_al_2022/</link>
<guid>/science/papers/guyot_et_al_2022/</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 20 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
<enclosure url="/science/papers/guyot_et_al_2022/Guyot%20et%20al.%20(2022),%20Detection%20of%20supercooled%20liquid%20water%20containing%20clouds%20with%20ceilometers%20development%20and%20evaluation%20of%20deterministic%20and%20data-driven%20retrievals.pdf" length="6550232" type="application/pdf" />
</item>







<item>
<title>Presentation | Machine learning of cloud types in satellite observations and climate models</title>
<author>Kuma et al.</author>
<description></description>
<link>https://zenodo.org/record/6551525</link>
<guid>https://zenodo.org/record/6551525</guid>
<pubDate>Fri, 13 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>

</item>







<item>
<title>Presentation | Software for climate sciences</title>
<author>Kuma</author>
<description></description>
<link>https://zenodo.org/record/6025116</link>
<guid>https://zenodo.org/record/6025116</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 09 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>

</item>







<item>
<title>Lecture | Global Climate System: Clouds and aerosols in the climate system</title>
<author></author>
<description></description>
<link>https://zenodo.org/record/5905868</link>
<guid>https://zenodo.org/record/5905868</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 25 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>

</item>







<item>
<title>Presentation | Clouds in climate models and atmospheric observations</title>
<author>Kuma</author>
<description></description>
<link>https://zenodo.org/record/5905775</link>
<guid>https://zenodo.org/record/5905775</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 14 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>

</item>







<item>
<title>Poster | Using deep learning cloud classiﬁcation in cloud feedback</title>
<author>Kuma and Bender</author>
<description></description>
<link>https://zenodo.org/record/5605067</link>
<guid>https://zenodo.org/record/5605067</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 27 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>

</item>







<item>
<title>Presentation | Machine learning of cloud types for evaluation of climate models and constraining climate sensitivity</title>
<author>Kuma and Bender</author>
<description></description>
<link>https://zenodo.org/record/5605043</link>
<guid>https://zenodo.org/record/5605043</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 25 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>

</item>







<item>
<title>Presentation | Using deep learning cloud classification for cloud feedback and climate sensitivity determination</title>
<author>Kuma and Bender</author>
<description></description>
<link>https://zenodo.org/record/5609454</link>
<guid>https://zenodo.org/record/5609454</guid>
<pubDate>Thu, 09 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>

</item>







<item>
<title>Media | How Airborne Microplastics Affect Climate Change</title>
<author></author>
<description></description>
<link>https://www.scientificamerican.com/article/how-airborne-microplastics-affect-climate-change1/</link>
<guid>https://www.scientificamerican.com/article/how-airborne-microplastics-affect-climate-change1/</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 20 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>

</item>







<item>
<title>Media | Microplastics May Be Cooling—and Heating—Earth’s Climate</title>
<author></author>
<description></description>
<link>https://www.wired.com/story/microplastics-may-be-cooling-and-heating-earths-climate/</link>
<guid>https://www.wired.com/story/microplastics-may-be-cooling-and-heating-earths-climate/</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 20 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>

</item>







<item>
<title>Media | Microplastics May Be Cooling—and Heating—Earth’s Climate</title>
<author></author>
<description></description>
<link>https://arstechnica.com/science/2021/10/microplastics-may-be-cooling-and-heating-earths-climate/</link>
<guid>https://arstechnica.com/science/2021/10/microplastics-may-be-cooling-and-heating-earths-climate/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 23 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>

</item>







<item>
<title>Media | Microplastics in the air have a small cooling effect on our climate</title>
<author></author>
<description></description>
<link>https://www.newscientist.com/article/2294440-microplastics-in-the-air-have-a-small-cooling-effect-on-our-climate/</link>
<guid>https://www.newscientist.com/article/2294440-microplastics-in-the-air-have-a-small-cooling-effect-on-our-climate/</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 20 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>

</item>







<item>
<title>Media | Microplastics are in the air we breathe and in Earth’s atmosphere, and they affect the climate</title>
<author></author>
<description></description>
<link>https://theconversation.com/microplastics-are-in-the-air-we-breathe-and-in-earths-atmosphere-and-they-affect-the-climate-170093</link>
<guid>https://theconversation.com/microplastics-are-in-the-air-we-breathe-and-in-earths-atmosphere-and-they-affect-the-climate-170093</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 20 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>

</item>







<item>
<title>Article | Direct radiative effects of airborne microplastics</title>
<author>Revell et al.</author>
<description>Microplastics are now recognized as widespread contaminants in the atmosphere, where, due to their small size and low density, they can be transported with winds around the Earth&lt;sup&gt;1,2,3,4,5,6,7,8,9,10,11,12,13,14,15,16,17,18,19,20,21,22,23,24,25&lt;/sup&gt;. Atmospheric aerosols, such as mineral dust and other types of airborne particulate matter, influence Earth’s climate by absorbing and scattering radiation (direct radiative effects) and their impacts are commonly quantified with the effective radiative forcing (ERF) metric&lt;sup&gt;26&lt;/sup&gt;. However, the radiative effects of airborne microplastics and associated implications for global climate are unknown. Here we present calculations of the optical properties and direct radiative effects of airborne microplastics (excluding aerosol–cloud interactions). The ERF of airborne microplastics is computed to be 0.044 ± 0.399 milliwatts per square metre in the present-day atmosphere assuming a uniform surface concentration of 1 microplastic particle per cubic metre and a vertical distribution up to 10 kilometres altitude. However, there are large uncertainties in the geographical and vertical distribution of microplastics. Assuming that they are confined to the boundary layer, shortwave effects dominate and the microplastic ERF is approximately −0.746 ± 0.553 milliwatts per square metre. Compared with the total ERF due to aerosol–radiation interactions&lt;sup&gt;27&lt;/sup&gt; (−0.71 to −0.14 watts per square metre), the microplastic ERF is small. However, plastic production has increased rapidly over the past 70 years&lt;sup&gt;28&lt;/sup&gt;; without serious attempts to overhaul plastic production and waste-management practices, the abundance and ERF of airborne microplastics will continue to increase.</description>
<link>/science/papers/revell_et_al_2021/</link>
<guid>/science/papers/revell_et_al_2021/</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 20 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
<enclosure url="/science/papers/revell_et_al_2021/Revell%20et%20al.%20(2022),%20Direct%20radiative%20effects%20of%20airborne%20microplastics.pdf" length="15715264" type="application/pdf" />
</item>







<item>
<title>Article | Southern Ocean Cloud and Aerosol data: a compilation of measurements from the 2018 Southern Ocean Ross Sea Marine Ecosystems and Environment voyage</title>
<author>Kremser et al.</author>
<description>Due to its remote location and extreme weather conditions, atmospheric in situ measurements are rare in the Southern Ocean. As a result, aerosol–cloud interactions in this region are poorly understood and remain a major source of uncertainty in climate models. This, in turn, contributes substantially to persistent biases in climate model simulations such as the well-known positive shortwave radiation bias at the surface, as well as biases in numerical weather prediction models and reanalyses. It has been shown in previous studies that in situ and ground-based remote sensing measurements across the Southern Ocean are critical for complementing satellite data sets due to the importance of boundary layer and low-level cloud processes. These processes are poorly sampled by satellite-based measurements and are often obscured by multiple overlying cloud layers. Satellite measurements also do not constrain the aerosol–cloud processes very well with imprecise estimation of cloud condensation nuclei. In this work, we present a comprehensive set of ship-based aerosol and meteorological observations collected on the 6-week Southern Ocean Ross Sea Marine Ecosystem and Environment voyage (TAN1802) voyage of RV Tangaroa across the Southern Ocean, from Wellington, New Zealand, to the Ross Sea, Antarctica. The voyage was carried out from 8 February to 21 March 2018. Many distinct, but contemporaneous, data sets were collected throughout the voyage. The compiled data sets include measurements from a range of instruments, such as (i) meteorological conditions at the sea surface and profile measurements; (ii) the size and concentration of particles; (iii) trace gases dissolved in the ocean surface such as dimethyl sulfide and carbonyl sulfide; (iv) and remotely sensed observations of low clouds. Here, we describe the voyage, the instruments, and data processing, and provide a brief overview of some of the data products available. We encourage the scientific community to use these measurements for further analysis and model evaluation studies, in particular, for studies of Southern Ocean clouds, aerosol, and their interaction. The data sets presented in this study are publicly available at &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4060237&quot;&gt;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4060237&lt;/a&gt; (Kremser et al., 2020).</description>
<link>/science/papers/kremser_et_al_2021/</link>
<guid>/science/papers/kremser_et_al_2021/</guid>
<pubDate>Fri, 02 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
<enclosure url="/science/papers/kremser_et_al_2021/Kremser%20et%20al.%20(2021),%20Southern%20Ocean%20cloud%20and%20aerosol%20data%20-%20a%20compilation%20of%20measurements%20from%20the%202018%20Southern%20Ocean%20Ross%20Sea%20Marine%20Ecosystems%20and%20Environment%20voyage.pdf" length="4415501" type="application/pdf" />
</item>







<item>
<title>Article | The winter 2019 air pollution (PM2.5) measurement campaign in Christchurch, New Zealand</title>
<author>Dale et al.</author>
<description>MAPM (Mapping Air Pollution eMissions) is a project whose goal is to develop a method to infer airborne particulate matter (PM) emissions maps from in situ PM concentration measurements. In support of MAPM, a winter field campaign was conducted in New Zealand in 2019 (June to September) to obtain the measurements required to test and validate the MAPM methodology. Two different types of instruments measuring PM were deployed: ES-642 remote dust monitors (17 instruments) and Outdoor Dust Information Nodes (ODINs; 50 instruments). The measurement campaign was bracketed by two intercomparisons where all instruments were co-located, with a permanently installed tapered element oscillating membrane (TEOM) instrument, to determine any instrument biases. Changes in biases between the pre- and post-campaign intercomparisons were used to determine instrument drift over the campaign period. Once deployed, each ES-642 was co-located with an ODIN. In addition to the PM measurements, meteorological variables (temperature, pressure, wind speed, and wind direction) were measured at three automatic weather station (AWS) sites established as part of the campaign, with additional data being sourced from 27 further AWSs operated by other agencies. Vertical profile measurements were made with 12 radiosondes during two 24 h periods and complimented measurements made with a mini micropulse lidar and ceilometer. Here we present the data collected during the campaign and discuss the correction of the measurements made by various PM instruments. We find that when compared to measurements made with a simple linear correction, a correction based on environmental conditions improves the quality of measurements retrieved from ODINs but results in over-fitting and increases the uncertainties when applied to the more sophisticated ES-642 instruments. We also compare PM2.5 and PM10 measured by ODINs which, in some cases, allows us to identify PM from natural and anthropogenic sources. The PM data collected during the campaign are publicly available from &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4542559&quot;&gt;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4542559&lt;/a&gt; (Dale et al., 2020b), and the data from other instruments are available from &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4536640&quot;&gt;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4536640&lt;/a&gt; (Dale et al., 2020a).</description>
<link>/science/papers/dale_et_al_2021/</link>
<guid>/science/papers/dale_et_al_2021/</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 18 May 2021 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
<enclosure url="/science/papers/dale_et_al_2021/Dale%20et%20al.%20(2021),%20The%20winter%202019%20air%20pollution%20(PM2.5)%20measurement%20campaign%20in%20Christchurch,%20New%20Zealand.pdf" length="6806082" type="application/pdf" />
</item>







<item>
<title>Poster | Climate sensitivity and the Southern Ocean: the effect of the &quot;too few, too bright&quot; model cloud problem</title>
<author>Kuma and Bender</author>
<description></description>
<link>https://zenodo.org/record/4707302</link>
<guid>https://zenodo.org/record/4707302</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 21 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>

</item>







<item>
<title>Article | Classification of the Below-Cloud Mixing State Over the Southern Ocean Using In-Situ and Remotely-Sensed Measurements</title>
<author>Hartery et al.</author>
<description>We demonstrate that the relationship between the abundance of particulate surface area observed at sea-level and measurements of backscattered light by a ceilometer can be used to classify the mixing state of the atmospheric layer beneath the lowest observed cloud, where the relationship is defined by the Spearman Rank correlation. The accuracy of this correlation-based method was compared to two methods of detecting boundary layer decoupling based on radiosonde measurements. An optimized version of the new methodology correctly determined the mixing state of the below-cloud layer for 76 &amp;plusmn; 4% of the radiosondes available for comparison. Further, it was more accurate than an alternative ground-based metric used to determine the below-cloud mixing state. For the majority of the time series in which the correlation analysis could be applied, the below-cloud boundary layer was well-mixed (54%), or else fog was present (27%), which indicated that aerosol particles observed at sea-level often have a direct pathway into low-cloud (81%). In the remaining analysis period, the near-surface atmospheric layer was stable and the atmospheric layer near the ocean surface was decoupled from the overlying cloud (19%). Forecasts from the Antarctic Mesoscale Prediction System also support our findings, showing that conditions that mix aerosol particles from the ocean surface to the lowest observed cloud occur 84% of the time over the open Southern Ocean. As a result, aerosol particles measured near sea-level are often tightly coupled to low-cloud formation over the Southern Ocean, highlighting the utility of shipborne aerosol observations in the region.</description>
<link>/science/papers/hartery_et_al_2021/</link>
<guid>/science/papers/hartery_et_al_2021/</guid>
<pubDate>Fri, 19 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>

</item>







<item>
<title>Article | Ground-based lidar processing and simulator framework for comparing models and observations (ALCF 1.0)</title>
<author>Kuma et al.</author>
<description>Automatic lidars and ceilometers (ALCs) provide valuable information on cloud and aerosols but have not been systematically used in the evaluation of general circulation models (GCMs) and numerical weather prediction (NWP) models. Obstacles associated with the diversity of instruments, a lack of standardisation of data products and open processing tools mean that the value of large ALC networks worldwide is not being realised. We discuss a tool, called the Automatic Lidar and Ceilometer Framework (ALCF), that overcomes these problems and also includes a ground-based lidar simulator, which calculates the radiative transfer of laser radiation and allows one-to-one comparison with models. Our ground-based lidar simulator is based on the Cloud Feedback Model Intercomparison Project (CFMIP) Observation Simulator Package (COSP), which has been extensively used for spaceborne lidar intercomparisons. The ALCF implements all steps needed to transform and calibrate raw ALC data and create simulated attenuated volume backscattering coefficient profiles for one-to-one comparison and complete statistical analysis of clouds. The framework supports multiple common commercial ALCs (Vaisala CL31, CL51, Lufft CHM 15k and Droplet Measurement Technologies MiniMPL), reanalyses (JRA-55, ERA5 and MERRA-2) and models (the Unified Model and AMPS – the Antarctic Mesoscale Prediction System). To demonstrate its capabilities, we present case studies evaluating cloud in the supported reanalyses and models using CL31, CL51, CHM 15k and MiniMPL observations at three sites in New Zealand. We show that the reanalyses and models generally underestimate cloud fraction. If sufficiently high-temporal-resolution model output is available (better than 6-hourly), a direct comparison of individual clouds is also possible. We demonstrate that the ALCF can be used as a generic evaluation tool to examine cloud occurrence and cloud properties in reanalyses, NWP models, and GCMs, potentially utilising the large amounts of ALC data already available. This tool is likely to be particularly useful for the analysis and improvement of low-level cloud simulations which are not well monitored from space.  This has previously been identified as a critical deficiency in contemporary models, limiting the accuracy of weather forecasts and future climate projections. While the current focus of the framework is on clouds, support for aerosol in the lidar simulator is planned in the future.</description>
<link>/science/papers/kuma_et_al_2021/</link>
<guid>/science/papers/kuma_et_al_2021/</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 06 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<enclosure url="/science/papers/kuma_et_al_2021/Kuma%20et%20al.%20(2021),%20Ground-based%20lidar%20processing%20and%20simulator%20framework%20for%20comparing%20models%20and%20observations%20(ALCF%201.0).pdf" length="8303305" type="application/pdf" />
</item>







<item>
<title>Dataset | Southern Ocean Cloud and Aerosol data set: a compilation of measurements from the 2018 Southern Ocean Ross Sea Marine Ecosystems and Environment voyage</title>
<author>Kremser et al.</author>
<description></description>
<link>https://zenodo.org/record/4060237</link>
<guid>https://zenodo.org/record/4060237</guid>
<pubDate>Fri, 30 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>

</item>







<item>
<title>Presentation | Doctoral thesis presentation: Comparing remotely sensed observations of clouds and aerosols in the Southern Ocean with climate model simulations</title>
<author>Kuma et al.</author>
<description></description>
<link>https://zenodo.org/record/5636022</link>
<guid>https://zenodo.org/record/5636022</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 07 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>

</item>







<item>
<title>Article | Evaluation of Southern Ocean cloud in the HadGEM3 general circulation model and MERRA-2 reanalysis using ship-based observations</title>
<author>Kuma et al.</author>
<description>Southern Ocean (SO) shortwave (SW) radiation biases are a common problem in contemporary general circulation models (GCMs), with most models exhibiting a tendency to absorb too much incoming SW radiation. These biases have been attributed to deficiencies in the representation of clouds during the austral summer months, either due to cloud cover or cloud albedo being too low. The problem has been the focus of many studies, most of which utilised satellite datasets for model evaluation. We use multi-year ship based observations and the CERES spaceborne radiation budget measurements to contrast cloud representation and SW radiation in the atmospheric component Global Atmosphere (GA) version 7.1 of the HadGEM3 GCM and the MERRA-2 reanalysis. We find that the prevailing bias is negative in GA7.1 and positive in MERRA-2. GA7.1 performs better than MERRA-2 in terms of absolute SW bias. Significant errors of up to 21 Wm&lt;sup&gt;−2&lt;/sup&gt; (GA7.1) and 39 Wm&lt;sup&gt;−2&lt;/sup&gt; (MERRA-2) are present in both models in the austral summer. Using ship-based ceilometer observations, we find low cloud below 2 km to be predominant in the Ross Sea and the Indian Ocean sectors of the SO. Utilising a novel surface lidar simulator developed for this study, derived from an existing COSP-ACTSIM spaceborne lidar simulator, we find that GA7.1 and MERRA-2 both underestimate low cloud and fog occurrence relative to the ship observations on average by 4–9% (GA7.1) and 18% (MERRA-2). Based on radiosonde observations, we also find the low cloud to be strongly linked to boundary-layer atmospheric stability and the sea surface temperature. GA7.1 and MERRA-2 do not represent the observed relationship between boundary layer stability and clouds well. We find that MERRA-2 has a much greater proportion of cloud liquid water in the SO in austral summer than GA7.1, a likely key contributor to the difference in the SW radiation bias. Our results suggest that subgrid-scale processes (cloud and boundary layer parametrisations) are responsible for the bias, and that in GA7.1 a major part of the SW radiation bias can be explained by cloud cover underestimation, relative to underestimation of cloud albedo.</description>
<link>/science/papers/kuma_et_al_2020a/</link>
<guid>/science/papers/kuma_et_al_2020a/</guid>
<pubDate>Fri, 05 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
<enclosure url="/science/papers/kuma_et_al_2020a/Kuma%20et%20al.%20(2020),%20Evaluation%20of%20Southern%20Ocean%20cloud%20in%20the%20HadGEM3%20general%20circulation%20model%20and%20MERRA-2%20reanalysis%20using%20ship-based%20observations.pdf" length="8026030" type="application/pdf" />
</item>







<item>
<title>Thesis | Comparing remotely sensed observations of clouds and aerosols in the Southern Ocean with climate model simulations</title>
<author>Kuma</author>
<description>Southern Ocean (SO) shortwave (SW) radiation biases are a common problem in contemporary general circulation models (GCMs), with most models exhibiting a tendency to absorb too much incoming SW radiation. These biases have been attributed to deficiencies in the representation of clouds during the austral summer months, either due to cloud cover or cloud albedo being too low. They affect simulation of New Zealand (NZ) and global climate in GCMs due to excessive heating of the sea surface and the effect on large-scale circulation. Therefore, improvement of GCMs is necessary for accurate prediction of future NZ and global climate. We performed ship-based lidar, radar, radiosonde and weather observations on two SO voyages and processed data from multiple past SO voyages. We used the observations and satellite measurements for evaluation of the Hadley Centre Global Environmental Model version 3 (HadGEM3) and contrasting with the Modern-Era Retrospective analysis for Research and Applications version 2 (MERRA-2) to better understand the source of the problem. Due to the nature of lidar observations (the laser signal is quickly attenuated by clouds) they cannot be used for 1:1 comparison with a model without using a lidar simulator, which performs atmospheric radiative transfer calculations of the laser signal. We modify an existing satellite lidar simulator present in the Cloud Feedback Model Intercomparison Project (CFMIP) Observational Simulator Package (COSP) for use with the ground-based lidars used in our observations by modifying the geometry of the radiative transfer calculations, Mie and Rayleigh scattering of the laser signal. We document and make the modified lidar simulator available to the scientific community as part of a newly-developed lidar processing tool called the Automatic Lidar and Ceilometer Framework (ALCF), which enables unbiased comparison between lidar observations and models by performing calibration of lidar backscatter, noise removal and consistent cloud detection. We apply the lidar simulator on HadGEM3 model fields. Significant SW radiation errors in the SO of up to 21 Wm⁻² are shown to be present in the model. Using the lidar observations, we find that the model underestimates overall cloud cover by about 9% and strongly underestimates boundary layer low-level stratocumulus (Sc) cloud below 1 km and fog. By using radiosonde observations, we find that the observed cloud was strongly linked to the boundary layer stability and sea surface temperature, while this relationship is weaker in the model. We identify that these errors are not due to misrepresentation of large-scale circulation, which is prescribed in our model based on global satellite observations by nudging. We conclude that the problem is likely in the subgrid-scale parametrisation schemes of the boundary layer, convection and large-scale could. In order to address the deficiencies identified we perform experimental simulations of HadGEM3 with modifications of the parametrisation schemes. We find that a three-layer cloud profiles were common in the Ross Sea region, consisting of cumulus (Cu) below Sc, and corresponding to local thermodynamic levels: lifting condensation level, dry and moist neutral buoyancy levels of parcels lifted from the surface. We find that not enough moisture is transported to the top of the boundary layer to form Sc clouds. By increasing surface moisture flux and convective mass flux in the model we improve the Sc cloud simulation, but we show that a lack of vertical moisture transport across the lifting condensation level from the surface layer to the zone of convective mass flux is a likely limiting factor. We show that the modifications had a positive impact on the Southern Ocean and global radiation balance of up to 5 Wm⁻² in zonal average over this limited time period. We suggest that further research should focus on the weak vertical coupling between the boundary layer turbulence and boundary layer convection parametrisation in the model, and that the lidar simulator framework is used as a cloud evaluation tool in further studies due to its benefits over more statistical approaches, which tend to hide compensating biases.</description>
<link>/science/theses/kuma_2020/</link>
<guid>/science/theses/kuma_2020/</guid>
<pubDate>Thu, 19 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<enclosure url="/science/theses/kuma_2020/Kuma%20(2020),%20Comparing%20remotely%20sensed%20observations%20of%20clouds%20and%20aerosols%20in%20the%20Southern%20Ocean%20with%20climate%20model%20simulations.pdf" length="53604124" type="application/pdf" />
</item>







<item>
<title>Article | The state of the atmosphere in the 2016 southern Kerguelen Axis campaign region</title>
<author>Klekociuk et al.</author>
<description>The near-surface environment of the Southern Ocean is subject to particular biases in weather and climate simulations, particularly during the summer season, and relatively few analyses of cloud and radiation properties have been reported for the region. Here we provide an analysis of ship-based measurements of downwelling radiation, cloud fraction and cloud base height from the RSV Aurora Australis during the Kerguelen Axis marine science campaign which was conducted in the Southern Ocean south-east of the Kerguelen Plateau between January and March 2016. Our study period focussed on a 22-day interval during the first two months of the campaign. We compared estimates of cloud fraction obtained with a cloud imager and ceilometer, and found good agreement between the two measurement types, particularly when the camera images were analysed in a narrow overhead field to account for differences in the measurement techniques. We used the Interim European Centre for Medium-Range Weather Forecasts Reanalysis (ERA-Interim) and the Antarctic Mesoscale Prediction System Polar Weather and Research Forecasting model (Polar WRF) to provide comparison data for our measurements. We found that both comparison data sets generally underestimated cloud cover (observed cloud fraction ~0.96 compared with 0.87 for ERA-Interim and 0.63 for Polar WRF). As a consequence, the comparison data showed biases in both the surface shortwave irradiance (+59 W m&lt;sup&gt;−2&lt;/sup&gt; for ERA-Interim and +154 W m&lt;sup&gt;−2&lt;/sup&gt; for Polar WRF) and the longwave irradiance (−23 W m&lt;sup&gt;−2&lt;/sup&gt; for ERA-Interim and −46 W m&lt;sup&gt;−2&lt;/sup&gt; for Polar WRF). The observed mean net surface cloud radiative effect (CRE) of −228 W m&lt;sup&gt;−2&lt;/sup&gt; was significantly more negative than found in previous observations in the Southern Ocean region, and compares with a net surface CRE of − 138 W m&lt;sup&gt;−2&lt;/sup&gt; for ERA-Interim which also showed relatively strong cloud forcing. The observed net surface CRE bias for ERA-Interim of + 90 W m&lt;sup&gt;−2&lt;/sup&gt; appears primarily the result of the reanalysis underestimating the cloud fraction, which at least partly relates to a lack of low clouds. Polar WRF was also found to have a deficit of low clouds. We characterised the relationship between the ratio of irradiances by Photosynthetically Active Radiation (PAR) and shortwave radiation and cloud transmittance. As a consequence of cloud, light levels were estimated as being below the level for light-limited photosynthesis during 31% of the available time the sun was above the horizon (69% of each day on average), compared with the expected clear-sky value of 10%. Over the campaign period, the Indian Ocean sector of the Southern Ocean was influenced by the positive phase of the Southern Annular Mode (SAM). Notably, the surface SAM index in January and March was the most positive observed since 1957. This situation generally led to near-surface climatological differences over the southern part of the campaign region over much of the period, which included significant negative anomalies in mean sea level pressure and air temperature, and positive anomalies in zonal wind. Overall, the cloudiness of our study region appeared to be above average for the time of year, but we could not identify a clear cause for this in the prevailing climatic conditions. While the level of shortwave radiation was likely below average for the time of year, this deficit is not likely to have significantly impacted on photosynthesis in the mixed layer of the ocean.</description>
<link>/science/papers/klekociuk_et_al_2020/</link>
<guid>/science/papers/klekociuk_et_al_2020/</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>

</item>







<item>
<title>Poster | Ground-based lidar processing and simulator framework for comparing models and observations</title>
<author>Kuma et al.</author>
<description></description>
<link>https://zenodo.org/record/3764299</link>
<guid>https://zenodo.org/record/3764299</guid>
<pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>

</item>







<item>
<title>Article | Constraining the Surface Flux of Sea Spray Particles from the Southern Ocean</title>
<author>Hartery et al.</author>
<description>Modeling the shortwave radiation balance over the Southern Ocean region remains a challenge for Earth system models. To investigate whether this is related to the representation of aerosol-cloud interactions, we compared measurements of the total number concentration of sea spray-generated particles within the Southern Ocean region to model predictions thereof. Measurements were conducted from a container laboratory aboard the R/V &lt;em&gt;Tangaroa&lt;/em&gt; throughout an austral summer voyage to the Ross Sea. We used source-receptor modeling to calculate the sensitivity of our measurements to upwind surface fluxes. From this approach, we could constrain empirical parameterizations of sea spray surface flux based on surface wind speed and sea surface temperature. A newly tuned parameterization for the flux of sea spray particles based on the near-surface wind speed is presented. Comparisons to existing model parameterizations revealed that present model parameterizations led to overestimations of sea spray concentrations. In contrast to previous studies, we found that including sea surface temperature as an explanatory variable did not substantially improve model-measurement agreement. To test whether or not the parameterization may be applicable globally, we conducted a regression analysis using a database of in situ whitecap measurements. We found that the key fitting parameter within this regression agreed well with the parameterization of sea spray flux. Finally, we compared calculations from the best model of surface flux to boundary layer measurements collected onboard an aircraft throughout the Southern Ocean Clouds, Radiation, Aerosol Transport Experimental Study (SOCRATES), finding good agreement overall.</description>
<link>/science/papers/hartery_et_al_2020/</link>
<guid>/science/papers/hartery_et_al_2020/</guid>
<pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>

</item>







<item>
<title>Poster | Automatic Lidar and Ceilometer Framework (ALCF)</title>
<author>Kuma et al.</author>
<description></description>
<link>https://zenodo.org/record/3764287</link>
<guid>https://zenodo.org/record/3764287</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 30 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>

</item>







<item>
<title>Poster | Evaluation of Southern Ocean cloud in the HadGEM3 general circulation model and MERRA-2 reanalysis using ship-based observations</title>
<author>Kuma et al.</author>
<description></description>
<link>https://zenodo.org/record/3764275</link>
<guid>https://zenodo.org/record/3764275</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 06 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>

</item>







<item>
<title>Presentation | Evaluation of HadGEM3 Southern Ocean cloud using observations and reanalyses</title>
<author>Kuma et al.</author>
<description></description>
<link>https://zenodo.org/record/5636003</link>
<guid>https://zenodo.org/record/5636003</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 05 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>

</item>







<item>
<title>Article | An analysis of the cloud environment over the Ross Sea and Ross Ice Shelf using CloudSat/CALIPSO satellite observations: The importance of synoptic forcing</title>
<author>Jolly et al.</author>
<description>We use the 2B-GEOPROF-LIDAR R04 (2BGL4) and R05 (2BGL5) products and the 2B-CLDCLASS-LIDAR R04 (2BCL4) product, all generated by combining CloudSat radar and CALIPSO lidar satellite measurements with auxiliary data, to examine the vertical distribution of cloud occurrence around the Ross Ice Shelf (RIS) and Ross Sea region. We find that the 2BGL4 product, used in previous studies in this region, displays a discontinuity at 8.2 km which is not observable in the other products. This artefact appears to correspond to a change in the horizontal and vertical resolution of the CALIPSO dataset used above this level. We then use the 2BCL4 product to examine the vertical distribution of cloud occurrence, phase, and type over the RIS and Ross Sea. In particular we examine how synoptic conditions in the region, derived using a previously developed synoptic classification, impact the cloud environment and the contrasting response in the two regions. We observe large differences between the cloud occurrence as a function of altitude for synoptic regimes relative to those for seasonal variations. A stronger variation in the occurrence of clear skies and multi-layer cloud and in all cloud type occurrences over both the Ross Sea and RIS is associated more with synoptic type than seasonal composites. In addition, anomalies from the mean joint histogram of cloud top height against thickness display significant differences over the Ross Sea and RIS sectors as a function of synoptic regime, but are near identical over these two regions when a seasonal analysis is completed. However, the frequency of particular phases of cloud, notably mixed phase and water, is much more strongly modulated by seasonal than synoptic regime compositing, which suggests that temperature is still the most important control on cloud phase in the region.</description>
<link>/science/papers/jolly_et_al_2018/</link>
<guid>/science/papers/jolly_et_al_2018/</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 10 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
<enclosure url="/science/papers/jolly_et_al_2018/Jolly%20et%20al.%20(2018),%20An%20analysis%20of%20the%20cloud%20environment%20over%20the%20Ross%20Sea%20and%20Ross%20Ice%20Shelf%20using%20CloudSat-CALIPSO%20satellite%20observations%20-%20the%20importance%20of%20synoptic%20forcing.pdf" length="2298071" type="application/pdf" />
</item>







<item>
<title>Poster | Shipborne and ground-based observations of clouds in the Southern Ocean</title>
<author>Kuma et al.</author>
<description></description>
<link>https://zenodo.org/record/3764269</link>
<guid>https://zenodo.org/record/3764269</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 19 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>

</item>







<item>
<title>Presentation | Doctoral Confirmation Presentation: Assessment of Southern Ocean Clouds and Aerosol in General Circulation Models</title>
<author>Kuma et al.</author>
<description></description>
<link>https://zenodo.org/record/5635851</link>
<guid>https://zenodo.org/record/5635851</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 09 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>

</item>







<item>
<title>Media | New Zealand’s Next Top Model</title>
<author></author>
<description></description>
<link>https://www.nzgeo.com/stories/esm/</link>
<guid>https://www.nzgeo.com/stories/esm/</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>

</item>







<item>
<title>Presentation | Assessment of Southern Ocean clouds and aerosols in the New Zealand Earth System Model using shipborne and ground-based observations</title>
<author>Kuma et al.</author>
<description></description>
<link>https://zenodo.org/record/5635689</link>
<guid>https://zenodo.org/record/5635689</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 13 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>

</item>







<item>
<title>Poster | Assessment of Southern Ocean clouds and aerosols in the New Zealand Earth System Model using shipborne and ground-based observations</title>
<author>Kuma et al.</author>
<description></description>
<link>https://zenodo.org/record/3764267</link>
<guid>https://zenodo.org/record/3764267</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 04 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>

</item>







<item>
<title>Poster | Shipborne and ground-based observations of clouds in the Subantarctic the the Southern Ocean</title>
<author>Kuma et al.</author>
<description></description>
<link>https://zenodo.org/record/3764265</link>
<guid>https://zenodo.org/record/3764265</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 26 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>

</item>







<item>
<title>Article | Single interval longwave radiation scheme based on the net exchanged rate decomposition with bracketing</title>
<author>Geleyn et al.</author>
<description>The main obstacle to efficient calculation of longwave radiative transfer is the existence of multiple radiative sources, each with its own emission spectrum. The work presented here overcomes this problem by combining the full spectrum broadband approach with the net exchanged rate decomposition. The idea is worked out to suit the needs of numerical weather prediction, where the most costly contribution representing the sum of internal exchanges is interpolated between cheap minimum and maximum estimates, while exchange with the surface and dominant cooling to space contributions are calculated accurately. The broad-band approach must address the additional problems related to spectral integration and many ideas developed previously for the solar spectrum are reused. Specific issues appear, the dependence of broadband gaseous transmissions on the temperature of the emitting body being the most important one. The thermal spectrum also brings some simplifications—aerosols, clouds and the Earth's surface can safely be treated as grey bodies. The optical saturation of gaseous absorption remains the main complication and non-random spectral overlaps between gases become much more significant than in the solar spectrum. The broadband character of the proposed scheme enables the use of an unreduced spatial resolution with an intermittent update of gaseous transmissions and interpolation weights, thus ensuring a full response of longwave radiation to rapidly varying cloudiness and temperature fields. This is in contrast to the mainstream strategy, where very accurate and expensive radiative transfer calculations are performed infrequently, often with reduced spatial resolution. The approach proposed here provides a much better balance between errors coming from the radiation scheme itself and from the intermittency strategy. The key achievement, ensuring a good scalability of the scheme, is a computational cost essentially linear in the number of layers, with straightforward inclusion of scattering as an additional bonus.</description>
<link>/science/papers/geleyn_et_al_2017/</link>
<guid>/science/papers/geleyn_et_al_2017/</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 17 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>

</item>







<item>
<title>Article | Single interval shortwave radiation scheme with parameterized optical saturation and spectral overlaps</title>
<author>Mašek et al.</author>
<description>Spectral integration is the most time consuming part of solar radiative transfer codes used in numerical weather prediction. Routinely used approaches usually incline to one of two extremes – expensive and very accurate correlated k-distribution method made affordable by doing radiative transfer calculations with reduced temporal and/or spatial resolution, or cheaper but less accurate broadband approach affordable at every grid-point and time-step. Both approaches have their pros and cons, but hybrid solutions do not seem very promising. The presented work improves accuracy of full spectrum broadband approach by parameterizing secondary saturation of gaseous absorption, optical saturation of Rayleigh scattering and of cloud absorption as well as non-random gas-cloud spectral overlap. In order to isolate the problem of spectral integration from other approximations, one builds a narrowband reference using the same delta-two stream framework as the broadband scheme. Using this reference reveals the surprising fact that saturation effect of cloud absorption for one single layer and for the whole solar spectrum can be parameterized in a rather compact way, with one simple formula for liquid clouds and one for ice clouds. One then introduces the concept of effective cloud optical depth, which extends the applicability of parameterized cloud optical saturation to multi-layer cases, accommodating also effects of gas-cloud spectral overlap in the near-infrared. A scheme with all the above parameterizations indeed pushes accuracy limits of broadband approach to the level where a single shortwave interval can be used. This opens the possibility to reduce costs by using selective intermittency, where slowly evolving gaseous transmissions are updated on the timescale of hours, while quickly varying cloud optical properties are recomputed at every model time-step. In a companion article it will be demonstrated that the above core strategy is applicable also to thermal radiative transfer, with perhaps even better cost effectiveness there.</description>
<link>/science/papers/masek_et_al_2015/</link>
<guid>/science/papers/masek_et_al_2015/</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 17 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>

</item>







<item>
<title>Thesis | Broadband approach as a framework for implementation of radiative transfer scheme with selective intermittency: Cost versus accuracy study</title>
<author>Kuma</author>
<description>The computational complexity of radiation schemes in NWP models precludes full radiative transfer calculations in every time step and every grid point of the model. Traditionally, models resort to calling a radiation scheme on a reduced temporal or spatial resolution, optionally scaling the resulting fluxes for the change in temperature profile and the solar zenith angle. As a result, the variability of cloud cover is neglected, leading to a considerable error. In the shortwave spectrum, relatively slowly changing gaseous optical properties are one of the most expensive parts to calculate. We propose a modification to the shortwave part of the ACRANEB2 broadband radiation scheme to interpolate gaseous optical thickness of layers with respect to the solar zenith angle within a chosen intermittency period, while still accounting for evolving cloudiness by recalculating its optical properties and the resulting fluxes via the adding method in every model time step. In this work we use a single column model to study the dependence of shortwave gaseous optical thickness on the solar zenith angle, we show that this dependence can be approximated with good accuracy, implement this approximation in the ACRANEB2 radiation scheme and assess the impact on accuracy of heating rates and model run time in 24-h simulations of the limited-area NWP model ALADIN. We show that the modification results in time saving of up to 4 % of total model run time and incurs error on shortwave heating rates up to ±0.4 K/day at noon (90 % confidence interval) and 0.06 K/day (MAE) over the whole domain and time period, and that both performance and accuracy scale with the length of the intermittency period. This relationship is summarised in a cost vs. accuracy comparison, giving potential users a guide on choosing the optimal intermittency period in their circumstances. The proposed modification became part of the ACRANEB2 radiation scheme implemented in package ALARO-1 version A, and since January 2015 it is operational in the model ALADIN/CHMI.</description>
<link>/science/theses/kuma_2015/</link>
<guid>/science/theses/kuma_2015/</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 09 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
<enclosure url="/science/theses/kuma_2015/Kuma%20(2015),%20Broadband%20approach%20as%20a%20framework%20for%20implementation%20of%20radiative%20transfer%20scheme%20with%20selective%20intermittency:%20Cost%20versus%20accuracy%20study%20simulations.pdf" length="3820189" type="application/pdf" />
</item>







<item>
<title>Thesis | Visualising Data from CloudSat and CALIPSO Satellites</title>
<author>Kuma</author>
<description>CloudSat and CALIPSO are NASA, resp. joint NASA and CNES polar-orbiting Earth observation satellites. CloudSat carries a millimetre-wave radar for observation of clouds. CALIPSO carries a visible and infrared polarisation-sensitive lidar for observation of aerosols and ice-phase clouds. Data from these satellites are distributed in the form of HDF4 and HDF-EOS2 product files. We introduce a software tool ccplot capable of visualising several data sets from the CloudSat 2B-GEOPROF, CALIPSO Lidar L1B Profiles, CALIPSO Lidar L2 Cloud Layer and Aqua MODIS L1B products. ccplot is a scriptable, unix command-line tool. We released ccplot on the Internet under the open-source-compatible BSD license.</description>
<link>/science/theses/kuma_2010/</link>
<guid>/science/theses/kuma_2010/</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 01 Jun 2010 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
<enclosure url="/science/theses/kuma_2010/Kuma%20(2010),%20Visualising%20Data%20from%20CloudSat%20and%20CALIPSO%20Satellites.pdf" length="9916592" type="application/pdf" />
</item>

</channel>
</rss>
